<article xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org"
         xmlns:omg="http://www.omegahat.org">
<title>Quick Introduction to the RCCS package</title>
<author>
<firstname>Duncan</firstname><surname>Temple Lang</surname>
</author>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>
This is a brief introduction to the <omg:pkg>RCSS</omg:pkg>
package.  It is intended to allow us to read Cascading Style Sheet (CSS) 
documents within R and to treat them as structured documents.
We can then list the different CSS rules, imports, etc.
in R to explore the contents of the CSS document. 
More interestingly, we can query the CSS document
for what style would be applied to a particular
XML (or HTML) node. In this way, we can check 
all the nodes in an XML document have a style,
find which styles are applied to which types of nodes
and determine what styles we have not implemented in
the CSS document.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Reading CSS files</title>
<para>
At present there are just a few functions in the package.  We start by
reading a CSS document with the <r:func>readCSS</r:func> function.
The primary argument in a call to this function provides the CSS
content.  This can be either the name of a local file or the CSS
content itself, i.e. an R string containing the CSS contents.  If the
file is local, we can give its name, e.g
<r:code>
f = system.file("samples", "eg.css", package = "RCSS")
css = readCSS(f)
</r:code> 
</para>
<para>
If the CSS material is available via a remote URL, then we can either
download it to a local file (e.g. <r:func>download.file</r:func>) and
use <r:func>readCSS</r:func> as before, or we can get its contents
with <r:func pkg="RCurl">getURLContent</r:func> in the
<omg:pkg>RCurl</omg:pkg> package.  With <r:func>getURLContent</r:func>, we
end up with the CSS content as a string <footnote><para>A character
vector of length 1</para></footnote>.  We can then pass this to
<r:func>readCSS</r:func> and specify that it is to be interpreted as
the text of the CSS content and not to be confused with a file name!
<r:code>
txt = getURLContent("http://www.omegahat.org/OmegaTech.css")
css = readCSS(txt, asText = TRUE)
</r:code>
We can also provide the text using the <r:func>I</r:func>
function in R to make it of class "AsIs":
<r:code>
css = readCSS(I(txt))
</r:code>
</para>
<para>
Alternatively, the CSS content might come from parsing an XML/HTML
file and taking the inlined CSS material.  
Let's look at an SVG file with an inlined CSS file
<r:code>
library(XML)
f = system.file("samples", "bob.svg", package = "RCSS")
doc = xmlParse(f)
node = getNodeSet(doc, "//x:style[@type='text/css']", "x")[[1]]
css = readCSS(I(xmlValue(node)))
</r:code>
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Working with the CSS object</title>
<para>
Now that we have the parsed  CSS object in R,
we can ask how many elements there are in the CSS
file via the <r:func>length</r:func> method,
<r:code>
 length(css)
</r:code>
In a limited way, we can think of the CSS object as a list.  We can
access individual elements using the [ and [[ operators, e.g
<r:code>
css[[1]]
css[1:2]
</r:code>
The elements these return are of the general class
<r:class>CSSStatement</r:class> but each will be of a class reflecting
a particular type of statement.  (This hierarchy reflects the
underlying libcroco library).  The classes are
<r:class>AT_RULE</r:class>, <r:class>RULESET</r:class>,
<r:class>IMPORT_RULE</r:class>, <r:class>MEDIA_RULE</r:class>,
<r:class>PAGE_RULE</r:class>, <r:class>CHARSET_RULE</r:class>,
<r:class>FONT_FACE_RULE</r:class>.
All of these are references to the C-level CSS statement objects.
They are not regular R objects. However, we can extract information
from them and convert them to R lists, etc.
</para>
<para>
We can ask for the names of the names of the elements
and we get back the CSS selectors as strings.
<r:code>
names(css)
</r:code>
</para>
<para>
We can convert a reference to a C-level CSS entry
to an R object using the generic function
<r:func>asCSSObject</r:func>.
For example, 
<r:code>
css = readCSS( system.file("samples", "eg.css", package = "RCSS") )
asCSSObject(css[[3]])
</r:code>
The different classes for the different types of CSS objects are all sub-classes
of the R class <r:class>CSSElement</r:class>.
These classes are 
<r:class>CSSRuleset</r:class>,
<r:class>CSSMediaRule</r:class>,
<r:class>CSSCharsetRule</r:class> and
<r:class>CSSFontFaceRule</r:class>.
(Neither <r:class>CSSPageRule</r:class> or
<r:class>CSSImportRule</r:class> seem to appear in the
list of CSS elements after the file has been read.)
</para>
<para>
When we convert a CSS element to an R object, we have access to the
details of the elements.  Converting a <r:class>RULESET</r:class>, we
end up with a <r:class>CSSRuleset</r:class>.  This has two slots:
declarations and selectors.  The selectors indicate to which nodes
this CSS element applies.  The declarations is a list of the
properties specific to this element.
<r:code>
library(RCSS)
css = readCSS(system.file("samples", "descendant.css", package = "RCSS"))
x = asCSSObject(css[[4]])  
x@declarations    
</r:code>
The elements of the <r:slot>declarations</r:slot> list are
<r:class>CSSDeclaration</r:class> objects.  Such objects have a
property name, a value and a level of importance.  The selectors give
the "rules" for which XML/HTML elements this CSS element 
applies.
</para>
<para>
We'll provide more information about these R-level classes in
the future. For now, explore the classes.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Resolving CSS elements for XML nodes</title>
<para>
One of the motivations for this package is to have the ability 
to be able to query a CSS file for an element 
that would apply to a particular XML or HTML node in a real document.
We can find which elements have no styles or simply
determine which CSS element applies and where it is located in the CSS.
</para>
<para>
We'll look at an HTML file, in fact the version for this very  document.
We'll find the associated CSS file
<r:code>
library(XML)
doc = htmlParse(system.file("doc", "guide.html", package = "RCSS"))
cssName = getNodeSet(doc, "//head/link[@rel='stylesheet' and @type='text/css']/@href")[[1]]
css = readCSS(cssName)
</r:code>
Now we have the CSS file and the HTML document and its nodes.
Let's look at the first h2 node and find its corresponding CSS rule, if there is one.
<r:code>
nodes = getNodeSet(doc, "//h2")
getCSSRules(nodes[[1]], css)
</r:code>
Unfortunately, at present the matching is case-sensitive even though the
CSS elements have an is_case_sensitive slot!
This seems to be an error in libcroco, but we'll dig into it more
to find a fix.
</para>
<para>
Let's look at an SVG file that is provided as an example in this package.
We'll find its inlined CSS document and then find all the path
nodes and see which of these are governed by an entry in the CSS document.
<r:code>
library(XML)
doc = xmlParse(system.file("samples", "bob.svg", package = "RCSS"))
txt = xmlValue(getNodeSet(doc, "//x:style[@type='text/css']", "x")[[1]])
css = readCSS(I(txt))
paths = getNodeSet(doc, "//x:path", "x")
rules = lapply(paths, getCSSRules, css)
table(sapply(rules, length))
</r:code>
So 29 of the 208 path nodes do not have a CSS entry.
</para>
<para>
If we are matching numerous XML/HTML nodes, it might
be of some value to create just once the selection engine
object used in the matching. Otherwise, a separate selection
engine will be created for each call to <r:func>getCSSRules</r:func>
and destroyed at the end of that call.
This is relatively cheap, but we can avoid it
by passing a selection engine object in
the call to <r:func>getCSSRules</r:func>.
<r:code>
  library(XML)
  doc = htmlParse("http://www.omegahat.org/index.html")
  allNodes = getNodeSet(doc, "//*")
  eng = selectionEngine()
  css = readCSS(system.file("samples", "OmegaTech.css", package = 'RCSS'))
  rules = lapply(allNodes, getCSSRules, css, eng)
  table(sapply(rules, length))
</r:code>
</para>
</section>
</article>
